<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">

<title>Comparison with other container systems</title>
<para>
This section compares the Rooms system with other similar tools.
Because the Rooms system is very new, some of the ideas here are not
fully implemented yet, but the intent is there.
</para>

<para>
	Rooms are easier to use than traditional FreeBSD jails because rooms
	provide a higher-level abstraction for expressing one's intent and desires
	about the container rather than having to engineer a precise solution
	and apply the corresponding jail configuration. Using room permissions,
	you can easily control what parts of the host system are shared with
	the container.
</para>

<para>
	When compared to iocage, rooms have a design that is more network-centric
	and allow you to share containers in much the same way as you can share a Git
	repository on GitHub. Rooms are structured so that local data is kept
	separate from shared data, so that when a new version or upgraded
	version of a room is available, you can install the updated software
	without overwriting your custom data.
</para>

<para>
	So to clarify, everything that you can do with rooms as possible to do
	with jails and iocage if you 2 Tinker with the low-level details and
	have a do it yourself mentality. Where it gets more interesting is when
	you want to share containers with the public, or pull from a public
	repository of containers. The design of traditional FreeBSD jails and
	iocage will not help you share a container.
</para>

<para>
	Another unique feature of rooms is that it is built as a library rather than a
	free-standing executable. This allows other software to work with rooms
	without having to fork() and exec() another program. (NOTE: the library is not ready for general use yet)
</para>

<para>
	Rooms also have a different approach to security than tools like iocage
	and
	ezjail. The room command is a setuid-root binary that is actively
	hardened against the user, and tries to make it difficult for the
	user
	to perform actions that might compromise the security of the whole
	system. The benefit of this is that users can be given permission to
	create their own containers. By contrast, think what would happen if
	you gave users the ability to
	create jails using iocage. They could
	easily use the exec_prestart
	option to run arbitrary commands as root in
	the host system.
</para>

<para>
	Another advantage of using rooms is that they will be integrated with the jobd
	service manager, so you will be able to launch jobs in the host system
	that run inside of a container. There will be various control knobs
	within the job configuration file to configure how the container works.
	None of	the existing jail managers will have this level of integration with
	jobd, so you will have to live with traditional mechanisms like rc(8) and cron(8).
</para>

<para>
	Rooms are also portable in a way that jail managers are not. A room is
	described at a higher level of abstraction than a jail, so it should be
	possible to implement rooms on a variety of different operating
	systems. On Linux, you would use cgroups to implement resource
	partitioning. On Solaris based systems, you would use zones. Having a
	container mechanism that works across multiple Unix variants is a
	compelling idea.
</para>

<!-- 
TODO: summarize
	- portable
	- secure enough to allow unprivileged users to create containers
	- version control system features
	- ease of use, especially when creating hybrid containers
-->
</section>
